Barr Ferree Collection, 1880s-1920s: Preliminary Finding Aid MC152
Manuscripts Division
Barr Ferree collection
1880s-1920s
Manuscripts Division
Ferree, Barr, 1862-1924.
MC152
23.75 linear feet 23 boxes
Consists of two groups of material collected by Ferree: 1) copies of government reports, resolutions, proclamations, statements, and clippings concerning foreign relations, the entry of the United States into World War I, and other varied issues during the administration of Woodrow Wilson.
Biographical / Historical
Bar Ferree was an Architectural historian.
Scope and Contents
Consists of two groups of material collected by Ferree: 1) copies of government reports, resolutions, proclamations, statements, and clippings concerning foreign relations, the entry of the United States into World War I, and other varied issues during the administration of Woodrow Wilson. Included are replies to Ferree's requests from the president's secretary, Joseph P. Tumulty. 2) The larger group consists of correspondence and ephemera relating to these general subjects: architecture, cathedrals of France, devastated France (after World War I), Egypt, flags, Germany, (World War I, the sinking of the Lusitania, etc.), libraries, London, museums, national politics (U.S.), New York, painting, Greece and Rome, and sculpture. Many of the letters are responses to Ferree's inquiries as secretary of the Pennsylvania Society of New York, which he founded.
Arrangement
The scrapbook material is arranged in subjects (from scrapbook spine titles) in alphabetical order: architecture, cathedrals of France, devastated France, Egypt, flags, Germany, libraries, London, museums, national, New York, painting, Greece and Rome, and sculpture.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no specific information about the acquisition of this collection. However, available information indicates that a large collection of books and materials were donated to Princeton's Marquand Library in 1925; it is possible that the materials that make up the Barr Ferree collection were part of this original gift.
Appraisal
Ther is no information about appraisal available for this collection.
Architecture.; Cathedrals -- France.; Flags.; Government publications -- United States -- 20th century.; Libraries.; Museums.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Causes.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Destruction and pillage -- France.; London (England); New York (State); United States -- Foreign relations -- 1913-1921.; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Press releases.; Scrapbooks.; American history/20th century; American politics and government; World War I; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924 -- Contributions in foreign relations.; Tumulty, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1879-1954.; Lusitania (Steamship); Pennsylvania Society of New York.
- Ferree, James Barr (1862-1924), Presidential messages, Proclamations, etc., 1881-1921; 7 folders
  - Diploma, Central HIgh School, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1881; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1913-1921; 6 folders
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1913-1914; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1915; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1916; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1917; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1919; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1920-1921; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes Suffrage Amendment, August-September 1920
- Cartoons/Cartoonists (+Posters), dates not examined; 2 Volumes (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Cathedrals of France, dates not examined; 14 Volumes (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cathedrals of France, dates not examined; 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Miscellaneous, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Architecture, dates not examined; 7 Volumes (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Devastated France, dates not examined; 3 Volumes (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Coins, dates not examined; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Egypt, dates not examined; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Flags, dates not examined; 3 Volumes (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Germany, dates not examined; 11 Volumes (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Libraries, dates not examined; 3 Volumes (Box 4, Folder 1)
- London, dates not examined; 8 Volumes (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Museums, dates not examined; 13 Volumes (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- National, dates not examined; 4 Volumes (Box 4, Folder 4)
- New York, dates not examined; 21 Volumes (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
- New York, dates not examined; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- Painting, dates not examined; 3 Volumes (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Greece and Rome, Undated; 8 Volumes (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Sculpture, dates not examined; 1 volume (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Topography England (empty), dates not examined; 2 Volumes (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Amiens I, II, 1914-1919; portion of 1 box (Box 7)
- Arras, 1914 June 20-September 30; portion of 1 box (Box 7)
- Cambrai I, II, 1914 September 26 - 1919 September 20; portion of 1 box (Box 7)
- Dardanelles Campaign I - XIV, 1915; 3 boxes (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9)
- Laon, 1915 July 24 - 1920 October 19; portion of 1 box (Box 9)
- Lille, 1914 December 9-1920 October 19; portion of 1 box (Box 9)
- London War I - III, 1914-1920; portion of 1 box (Box 10)
- New York War, 1917-1921; portion of 1 box (Box 10)
- Barr Ferree collection, 1915-1920; portion of 1 box (Box 10)
- Paris I - XVIII, 1914-1921; 2 boxes (Box 10, Box 11)
- Reims I - XLV, 1914-1923; 7 boxes (Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
- Strasbourg Metz, 1918-1920; portion of 1 box (Box 18)
- Soissons, 1914-1920; portion of 1 box (Box 18)
- Verdun I to XXXVI, 1914-1923; 6 boxes (Box 18, Box 19, Box 20)